A Guide to the Papers of James A. Brewer, 1729, 1969
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
James A. Brewer Papers, 1729,1969
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1978-25
James Brewer, a graduate of Virginia State was later a member of the faculty teaching in the Department of History. While a member of the faculty, Professor Brewer collected a number of papers regarding manumissions of blacks in several counties in North Carolina. Included is a petition for the self-hire of slaves in Wilmington, North Carolina. There is also some correspondence documenting some of Mr. Brewer's activities as a resident of Ettrick.
James A. Brewer
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Biographical/Historical Information
James A. Brewer, a Petersburg native and graduate of Virginia State College for Negroes in 1941. After World War II Mr. Brewer returned to school earning both the M.A. and Ph. D in History from Pennsylvania State in Pennsylvania. Mr. Brewer began his teaching career in North Carolina and later joined the faculty at Virginia State University.
Scope and Content Information
Research documents mainly concerned with slavery and manumission in Wilmington North Carolina.
Series Description
Series I. Correspondence Some correspondence generated by Professor Brewer while a resident of Ettrick Virginia.
Series II. A group of paper documenting several freed African-Americans in the state of North Carolina.
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - General Correspondence 1957-1963 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Ettrick Community Asscoiation 1960-1969 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - VSU Graduate School Correspondence 1953-1962 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - VSU Alumni Association 1953 (Box-folder 1:4)
- Historical Documents
  - Petition for Emancipation 1792 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Slave Buying Freedom 1792-1793 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Wife Buying and Freeing Husband 1793-1794 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Emancipation Papers 1800 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Hiring Out 1835 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Writings (Box-folder 1:12)